<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2026-01-28T16:08:11-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Listening in high fidelity</title><subtitle>Technical notes from Rob Arnold on the pursuit of better listening experiences.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Storing my record collection</title><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/diy/2026/01/28/storing-my-collection-part-1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Storing my record collection" /><published>2026-01-28T08:06:17-06:00</published><updated>2026-01-28T08:06:17-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/diy/2026/01/28/storing-my-collection-part-1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/diy/2026/01/28/storing-my-collection-part-1.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="storage-goals">Storage goals</h2>

<p>When you have too many records, getting to the spot where the one you want to play is stored is a challenge. Since the 1980’s I’ve used corrugated storage cartons for my collection. They are terrible for browsing though, even though I have to say they kept my collection in great condition over a couple decades of not accessing the records.</p>

<p>So my start point on the storage journey was records in clear outer sleeves, stored in corrugated cartons, of which I accumulated about 12.</p>

<p>I decided it needed to be a lot more browse friendly. So I took the opportunity to build a shelf unit that I thought would accomplish my goal of a better browse experience. This post is about the process that culminated in that furniture being installed.</p>

<h2 id="sketching-it-out">Sketching it out</h2>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_0710.jpeg" alt="early drawing of the design of my record furniture" /></p>

<p>My initial thoughts revolved around a 4-foot long cabinet that would be roughtly 2 feet tall, in order to hold two shelves of LPs (which are about 12-1/4 inches in outer jackets). Keeping it simple, I planned a rectngular carcass with an open back (I thought about partial stops tht keep the records from sliding too far back in the opening–it’s a good idea that I chose to skip). Then my gear can sit on top of the shelf. Iron hairpin legs keep the carcass off the floor.</p>

<p>The idea of the vertical dividers initially was to give me a space to slide a 12 inch storage cube (kind of a common size, Ikea and others sell these in several styles) to hold my “Accessories” that I didn’t want to put on display but need to be close at hand.</p>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_0712.jpeg" alt="later dimensioned drawing of the design of my record furniture" /></p>

<p>I figured the height of the openings at 13 inches, but at build time I added an inch, which was a super good decision. The boards I used for this were glueups made from Aspen wood, finished on four sides and 48” x 11-1/2” x 3/4”. Keeping the shelves as long as possible meant leaving the horizontal boards uncut–all the cuts were for the vertical pieces.</p>

<h2 id="initial-test-assembly">Initial test assembly</h2>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_7396.jpeg" alt="cut pieces being &quot;dry fit&quot;" /></p>

<p>Before getting out the pocket hole jig and drilling, I checked my pieces for fit by laying it out on the shop floor.</p>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_7397.jpeg" alt="assembled carcass" /></p>

<p>I don’t have pics of the pocket holes or jig but if you’ve used one, you know it make simple joinery like this go pretty quick. I got the box put together in under an hour, almost as if it were a kit rather than custom designed.</p>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_7452.jpeg" alt="shot of the top being finished&quot;" /></p>

<p>For me the most controversial choice was using water based polyurethane finish–Amy didn’t want it to show any yellowing, which normal poly will give you. To increase the Wife Acceptance Factor (WAF) we used the water-based stuff. It’s quite clear and this is after maybe six coats where I sanded between applications.</p>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_7464.jpeg" alt="finished with legs attached&quot;" /></p>

<p>And once I felt like more coats of poly was not going to inproe it, I added the legs. Astute readers will notice I places the accessory bin spot in the upper shelf unlike in my sketch. It seemed like a better design choice, and it also let me use the nicer shelf as the top. Haha, I immediately filled it with records anyway instead of using it as designed.</p>

<h2 id="dimensions-and-stuff">Dimensions and stuff</h2>

<p>I estimate this holds about 500 records, plus or minus 10%. I did not really put enough thought into the weight and how the span would sag. I’d say there’s a 1/4” sag in the horizontal shelves (measured between the center and ends) and fortunately my leveling feet on my turntable allow me to compensate. If I rebuild or replace this, i’ll stiffen it by adding the stop boards in the back of the openings. I would also like it if I had better lighting when selecting a record, maybe that goes into version 2.0.</p>

<p>The 11-1/2” depth is not really enough for my vintage components to securely sut on, so I am just resting an unfinished board that is 16” deep on the top of the unit. I may choose to wall-mount that board as a shelf, thereby further decoupling the equipment from being disturbed when I pull or replace a record from the rack.</p>

<p>If I find a nice chunk of butcher block countertop that is long enough, I’ll add that to the top of this but fhe cheap board hack is working for now.</p>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_7654.jpeg" alt="installed in the space with zero records&quot;" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Updated on 2026-01-28</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Rob Arnold</name></author><category term="audio" /><category term="hifi" /><category term="DIY" /><category term="furniture" /><category term="LPs" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[When you have too many records]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How did you do the rad videos?</title><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/video/demo/measurement/meta/2026/01/09/video-stunts.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How did you do the rad videos?" /><published>2026-01-09T20:28:23-06:00</published><updated>2026-01-09T20:28:23-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/video/demo/measurement/meta/2026/01/09/video-stunts</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/video/demo/measurement/meta/2026/01/09/video-stunts.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="the-tricksy-bit">The tricksy bit</h2>

<p>I did a first set of videos where I had my meter in one hand and my phone in the other, and I walked around and it was nauseatingly bad. The worst. So I decided to build a jig to hold my meter and camera at a fixed distance so I can maybe not induce vomiting.</p>

<h2 id="scrap-lumber-and-pocket-hole-screws">scrap lumber and pocket hole screws</h2>

<p>90% of this is two boards I screwed together at a right angle. Then the other super advanced technology is a bunch of holes I drilled so I can use a 1/4-20 threaded knob to mount my meter and my phone grabber/holder. A bunch of camera mount stuff is 1/4-20 so I have some experience hacking mounts to meet my needs. Wallace and Gromit would be proud of some of my contraptions.</p>

<h2 id="shut-up-and-show-it-to-me">shut up and show it to me</h2>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_0646.jpeg" alt="Patent pending camera meter holderizer" /></p>

<p>I was getting distracting reflections in the meter lens so I used the white paper to get rid of that. If I use this more than 1-2 more times I may make a nicer version from <em>better</em> scrap lumber and paint it white instead.</p>

<p>Pretty cool, eh?</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Updated on 2026-01-09</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Rob Arnold</name></author><category term="audio" /><category term="video" /><category term="demo" /><category term="measurement" /><category term="meta" /><category term="setup" /><category term="site" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In which I reveal some but not all my tricks]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">See how it sounds</title><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/08/see-how-it-sounds.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="See how it sounds" /><published>2026-01-08T18:36:17-06:00</published><updated>2026-01-08T18:36:17-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/08/see-how-it-sounds</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/08/see-how-it-sounds.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="no-really-this-is-kind-of-the-entire-point">No really this is kind of the entire point</h2>

<p>The best reason to take these absurdly detailed acoustic measurements in your room is so you can see and more easily perceive defects in your listening setup that you can (ideally) do something about. Hopefully you do something that makes it better. And hopefully you show with additional measurements that it <em>is</em> better, and how much better. And onward and upward.</p>

<h2 id="ok-so-you-moved-your-couch">OK, so you moved your couch</h2>

<p>The first question under consideration is “did it help or hurt” and for that evaluation we’re gonna use Room EQ Wizard (REW). I blathered endlessly about why it should be a good idea in a previous post, but now we get to find out if it really was a (measurable) improvement. Because confirmation bias is a hell of a thing.</p>

<h2 id="quick-detour-confirmation-bias">Quick detour: confirmation bias</h2>

<p>Confirmation bias works against all of us in subtle ways. I think of it as a bug in human firmware. You can know you suffer from it, which is better than not knowing, but you can’t just turn it off. It’s not really a weakness or a defect, but it’s there and it has real effects.</p>

<p>How confirmation bias works is you show up to any evaluation with some prior beliefs about how things work. And you go ahead and collect some observations in order to form some conclusions. And your brain has evolved to have a tendency to disregard the observations that don’t confirm your prior beliefs, and give more significance to the observations that do.</p>

<h2 id="cmon-man-make-wth-the-graphs">C’mon man, make wth the graphs</h2>

<p>All right, this is what I started this blog for after all.</p>

<p><img src="/i/couch-effect-spl.png" alt="SPL chart comparing two listening positions" /></p>

<p>This chart illustrates the measured SPL at the listening position for two different placements of my couch. Yellow trace shows away from the back wall, blue is closer to the back wall (where a normal person would put their couch). When I measured, I actually did <em>six</em> sweeps, even though I’m showing you two of them. The L and R channel behave distinctly differently, and those differences can be diagnostic when it comes time to evaluate correcting problems. So I gathered more details than I am showing you right now.</p>

<p>Very impressive, but what do we learn from this picture? Imagine for a moment a perfect frequency response, where the room contributes nothing and the speakers were absolutely ideal at all frequencies–that would appear as a horizontal line. So you can think of any deviation from that ideal as a defect. One of the challenges is identifying and corrrecting that defect (okay that’s two of the challenges). Let’s focus on identifying: when the line drops a bunch, that’s a null. That means that <em>at the listening position,</em> there’s a drop in the amplitude at a speciific frequency (shown on the x-axis of our chart), and it’s kind of up to us to determine why (comb filter, room mode, or maybe some other thing we aven’t talked about).</p>

<p>The wider and deeper that notch on the chart is, the likelier that it is a <em>perceptible</em> defect in the sound. Especially in the higher frequencies, a lot of variation is expected and not particulary significant in terms of a perceptible effect on our music. To get more specific, we are hunting bass-sucking effects. So we can adjust the chart limits and “zoom in” a bit on the area from 20 Hz to 600 Hz. Which I have done before exporting this chart (I certainly measured the room up to 20kHz, and those numbers are in the file REW saves).</p>

<p>Two features present themselves as worth some investigation: there are notches at 90 Hz and 125 Hz. You can point at the one between 40 and 50 Hz, but it affects both positions, so it’s a little less interesting to investigate to me (maybe my speakers are contributing that, or perhaps any other thing that’s not couch placement). Notice that the overall SPL is higher for the closer listening position–I was quite careful to leave everything else the same as I varied my listening position between measurements. Sounds get fainter as you move away from them (a thing you certainly knew before you got here).</p>

<p>Let’s investigate the 90 Hz notch. The procedure here is grabbing my handheld sound meter and kind of moving it around in space to see (and hear) how localized that notch is (spoiler: super localized). To really make the demo vivid, the input signal is a sine wave at 90 Hz, which is free of information that is <em>not</em> going to trigger that effect. We’re expecting a big change in the meter reading as we get to the listening position (where the yellow curve measurement above was taken).</p>

<video controls="" preload="metadata" width="640">
  <source src="/i/sine-test.webm" type="video/webm" />
  <source src="/i/sine-test.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>

<p>The effect is quite vivid, around 15 dB lower, which tracks what we see on the graph nicely. It’s quite a bit worse when only the Right channel is putting energy into the room. Having the Left speaker also provide the test signal lessens this notch, but also reflects how I would normally use my system.</p>

<p>Other waveforms besides sine waves have additional frequencies (harmonic content) besides the fundamental. And that generally inclused real world musical instruments of all sorts and vocalists. So I’ll repeat the test but with a sawtooth wave. The harmonics aren’t affected by the notch, only the fundamental is. And human hearing is quite amazing–it <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Missing_fundamental">infers</a> the presence of the fundamental from the harmonics, even when the actual signal is not there. That’s really wild, and we knew about this in the 1950’s.</p>

<video controls="" preload="metadata" width="640">
  <source src="/i/saw-test.webm" type="video/webm" />
  <source src="/i/saw-test.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>

<p>As a final demo and to maybe point more at the audible effect of the notch, check out the same procedure done with pink noise as a source. More so than watching the meter change numbers, listen for the sound changing as I move. This happens in just about any real listening environment–where you are can make very perceptible sound changes.</p>

<video controls="" preload="metadata" width="640">
  <source src="/i/noise-test.webm" type="video/webm" />
  <source src="/i/noise-test.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>

<p>You, the alert reader, undoubtedly noticed that I called out a 77 dB reading when the meter shows 71 dB (until I started yapping).</p>

<p>So we measured this, we confirmed our measurement with some further testing, and now we need to evaluate–is this a problem that is worth correcting? Did I move my heavy couch for nothing? Are we winning?</p>

<p>I haven’t reached a final conclusion just yet, but I think the 90 Hz notch at the forward position bugs me more than the 125 Hz notch with the couch back. Maybe I can find a middle placement that avoids both of them (and ideally won’t introduce something more obnoxious). I did a similar checkout with the 125 Hz notch, but I won’t bore you with the videos. It occupies a much narrower slice of the spectrum, and it’s less noticeable even though in absolute measurement terms it’s lower.</p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next steps</h2>

<p>This thing is getting kind of long, so I’ll let you know what I have concluded so far, what additional investigation I want to do, then I’ll wrap this up. I think both couch positions are defective, but neither one is unacceptable (unless I get into listening to sine waves instead of music). I also suspect that splitting the difference could keep me away from sitting right in the 90 Hz notch. That suggests another set of measurements to be taken with the LP at about 27” off the rear wall. As lnog as that doesn’t introduce a worse null, it will avoid both of these. The narrower but deeper notch is way less perceptible with musical content. Not even close. So the current best case is the 18” from wall spot, but I want to test and see if 27” beats it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Updated on 2026-01-08</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Rob Arnold</name></author><category term="audio" /><category term="hifi" /><category term="setup" /><category term="measurement" /><category term="acoutsicts" /><category term="REW" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Haha any dumbass knows you can't see sound]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Dude where’s my couch</title><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/07/dude-wheres-my-couch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dude where’s my couch" /><published>2026-01-07T18:36:02-06:00</published><updated>2026-01-07T18:36:02-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/07/dude-wheres-my-couch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/07/dude-wheres-my-couch.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>

<p>I think in this post I’ll attempt to describe the theory of moving my couch, and have the empirical results be a separate post. Is that because I’m too lazy to do it all today? Who can say, really?</p>

<h2 id="comb-filters">Comb filters</h2>

<p>Understanding comb filter effects is a significant enough thing that my acoustics book spends the entire chapter 5 developing the theory. Let me try to cook that down to the highlights.</p>

<p>When a signal is present along with a delayed copy of itself, then there will be peaks that line up, making the signal louder, as well as points where a peak coincides with a valley, which will tend to cancel it out. From the time of the delay, you can predict or model where the pakes and valleys fall in the frequency spectrum.</p>

<p>My couch began its journey today at a distance from the wall that places my head at 18” distance from the rear wall of my listening room. We can use the speed of sound to figure that (1.5 ft) / (1130 ft/s) gives a delay of 1.3 ms between the signal that hits my ear fresh out of the speaker and the delayed reflection from the back wall. That will result in a null at 1/(2t) Hz or 376 Hz. But that’s just the first null. You get one every 753 Hz. And peaks and nulls will occur evry 753 Hz after that. The closer the amplitude of the reflection is to the original signal, the more severe the peaks and nulls are.</p>

<p>Now, all that is very tidy for drawing on graphs and such, but can you hear those nulls? There has been some research about this, but more needs to occur. From my book, we learn that:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Single peaks are easier to perceive than dips of the same magnitude</li>
  <li>Single dips an octave wide are easily perceived at 10 dB depth</li>
  <li>Single dips an octavve wide at 5 dB are at the threshold of perceptible</li>
  <li>Narrower dips are harder to perceive</li>
</ul>

<p>These tests were done with music and speech. Frequency plays a role too, but we can kind of get a sense of how severe a null needs to be to become a real problem from these heuristics. Remeber an octave is the distance between a frequency and double that frquency, such as 200-400Hz. So maybe comb filter effects aren’t super hazardous, unless they fall into the more perceptible kinds of conditions.</p>

<h2 id="moving-away">Moving away</h2>

<p>If I can’t make the wall less reflective, a good strategy is to move farther from it. Today for reasons unrelated to acoustic perfection (I was changing some light bulbs) I moved my couch out and decided I would measure the effects of doing it on the reflections I get from the rear wall. Ideally, such as outdoors, you get zero reflections from behind, so nothing interferes or distorts the pristing sound arriving from in front of you.</p>

<p>But getting my ladder behind the couch allowed me to move my listeing position to 36” off the rear wall. Keeping the math super simple, just double my numbers from above–the first null is at 753 Hz, with copies at every 1,506 Hz onward.</p>

<p>At least in theory, that rules. The null due to the reflection is now moved out of bass and into midrange territory. So I’m way less likely to perceive any comb filtering effects at making the bass or kick drum sound wimpy. And the wider spacing between those nulls means fewer of them show up across the audio spectrum. All good, at least in theory.</p>

<h2 id="next-steps">Next Steps</h2>

<p>Tomorrow I’ll try to post about the actual observed result of the move. I have a way to compare the two listening positions directly, and we can go over how well theory predicts the experimental result of moving my ridiculously heavy couch around. And whether it <em>might not be worth the fight</em> to leave it where it is now.</p>

<p>If my explanation of constructive and destructive interference above left you unsatisfied, go check out <a href="https://audiouniversityonline.com/comb-filtering-explained/">Audio University</a> where they also show some cool visual depictions of the effect, along with recordings so you can hear it.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Updated on 2026-01-07</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Rob Arnold</name></author><category term="audio" /><category term="hifi" /><category term="setup" /><category term="acoustics" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In which we examine my motivations for moving a large piece of furniture around]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Talking about measurement</title><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/06/talking-about-measurement.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Talking about measurement" /><published>2026-01-06T08:30:25-06:00</published><updated>2026-01-06T08:30:25-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/06/talking-about-measurement</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/06/talking-about-measurement.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="terms-and-conditions">Terms and conditions</h2>

<p>One of the things that makes this a technical blog instead of some random crank expressing opinions is that I will try my best to precisely use technical terms and units to describe the things I’m talking about. So, a random crank <em>with an engineering degree</em> expressing opinions <em>with precision</em>. With the caveat that I don’t work in the engineering field.</p>

<p>On this page, I’ll try to condense down the most important parts that I learned from an entire course I took called “Electrical measurements” and combine that with a few things from audio engineering and from music theory that I thing will help us have that more precise conversation. Maybe this page can be a helpful guidepost in later posts.</p>

<h2 id="things-to-know-about-measurements">Things to know about measurements</h2>

<p>Measurements have error. Error is the difference between the true quantitiy and the measured quantity. Error can be observational or systematic.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>If a 1kg calibrated reference mass gives you a scale reading of 999g, that is a 1g error. If the error is consistent across repeated measurements, that is systematic error. If my scale isn’t clean because I was making bread and got four on it, that could be a source of observational error. My coffee scale (which I love and use for all kinds of things) is rated to be accurate with a one gram error in the range from 500-2000g (see the tiny writing on the scale).
<img src="/i/IMG_0337.jpeg" alt="scale getting calibrated kind of" /></p>
</blockquote>

<p>People who take measurements seriously tend to state the uncertainty in their measurements, in order to convey both the accuracy and precision. We could say that scale reads 1000g ±1g.</p>

<p>Even without a statement of uncertainty, the number of significant digits in a measurement can imply a precision. We can say that scale reads 1.00 kg or 1.00 x 10<sup>3</sup>g to express 10 gram precision, or 1.000 kg or 1.000 x 10<sup>3</sup> g to express 1 gram precision.</p>

<p>Okay, what’s up with the exponents? If you are bummed out by the 10<sup>3</sup> notation, just know that it is very convenient when the quantities vary fairly widely over a range, and allows expression of the precision separately from the magnitude, and also make it much easier to multiply (or divide) numbers by adding (or subtracting) their exponents. 4.2 x 10<sup>8</sup> / 2 x 10<sup>3</sup> is easy to do in your head: divide the coefficients (4.2 / 2 = 2.1) and then subtract the exponents (8 - 3 = 5) giving you 2.1 x 10<sup>5</sup>.</p>

<h2 id="electrical-quantities-to-know">Electrical quantities to know</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Volt: Measures the electical potential difference between two points.</li>
  <li>Amp: Measures the magnitude of the electrical current, which has a direction.</li>
  <li>Watt: Measures the electrical power; equal dimensionally to current x voltage.</li>
  <li>Ohm: Measures the resistance to the flow of current or impedance to a time-varying current. The abbreviation is Ω (capital omega–we use lowercase for different things)</li>
  <li>Hertz: Measures frequency; equivalent to “per second” or s<sup>-1</sup>.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="audio-quantities-to-know">Audio quantities to know</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Frequency, measured in Hz (Hertz), is equivalent to cycles per second. Any time-varying signal (eletrical or sound pressure) can be measured this way for frequency.</li>
  <li>Sound pressure level, mesured in B (bels) or more commonly dB (decibels) is defined by reference to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Absolute_threshold_of_hearing">a threshold level</a> at the lower limit of human hearing. This may deserve its own post, but for now, know that audio loudness expressed in dB is shorthand for “dB SPL,” which refers to that 20 micropascal pressure that corresponds to the quietest sound humans can perceive. Hearing has enormous dynamic range, and so the threshold of pain is somewhere around or above 120 dB SPL, depending on frequency.</li>
  <li>dB units are dimensionless–anything measured in dB is actually a ratio between some measurement and the reference point which has the identical dimensions. Therefore the numerator and denominator dimensions cancel and dB are “dimensionless.” So it can be tricky or confusing to know exactly what quantity is being expressed, although usually from context you can figure it out. We won’t go crazy deep into audio engineering where the going gets rougher as yoou model gain staging through a complex signal chain, so most of the time on this blog dB will refer to dB SPL, or how loud the sound is. I’ll try to label other usages clearly in the interests of <strike>being a giant nerd</strike> precision and clarity of expression.</li>
  <li>83 dB SPL is a sort of <em>de facto</em> reference level for listening critically, such as during mixing or mastering. This is a recommendation from SMPTE, the Society of Motion Picture and Television Engineers. The tradeoffs are this is loud enough that the frequency response is flatter (than at quieter levels) but not so loud to be fatiguing.</li>
  <li>1 dB (change, not an absolute level in SPL) is about the smallest perceptible change in level.</li>
  <li>3 dB corresponds to twice the power in Watts (-3 dB to half). So if your system generates a level of 77 dB sPL with 1 Watt applied, applying 2 watts will generate an 80 dB SPL.</li>
  <li>6 dB corresponds to twice the pressure/level/loudness. It takes 4 times the power to achieve.</li>
  <li>10 dB corresponds to a tenfold increase in power.</li>
  <li>20 dB is a tenfold increase in loudness, and a 100-fold increase in power.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="musical-quantities-to-know">Musical quantities to know</h2>

<ul>
  <li>An octave is the pitch distance between two muscial notes that share the same name (pitch class). In musical terms, 440Hz is defined as A4 by international standard <a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/3601.html">ISO 16:1975</a>. A5 is one octave above A4, and is 880Hz. A6 is twice the frequency of A5. A3 (220Hz) is half the frequency of A4.</li>
  <li>Harmonics are the music theory term for integer multiples of a fundamental frequency. Physical objects that vibrate tend to also vibrate at a series of multiples of their fundamental frequency.</li>
</ul>

<p>Knowing stuff, it’s cool!</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Updated on 2026-01-06</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Rob Arnold</name></author><category term="audio" /><category term="hifi" /><category term="measurement" /><category term="audio" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In which we discuss precision, accuracy, and dimensions]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">How’s your hearing?</title><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/05/hows-your-hearing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How’s your hearing?" /><published>2026-01-05T10:10:30-06:00</published><updated>2026-01-05T10:10:30-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/05/hows-your-hearing</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/05/hows-your-hearing.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="old-guys-dont-hear-so-good">Old guys don’t hear so good</h1>

<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>

<p>Before wasting a bunch of electrons writing about how good my room and/or system sounds, I thought it may be useful to examine my own sense of hearing.</p>

<p>Today’s post is brought to you by the word <a href="https://www.nidcd.nih.gov/health/age-related-hearing-loss">presbycusis</a>, which is age-related hearing loss.</p>

<p>So just maybe I’m one of the many afflicted people, and you should discount anything I have to say about music or whatever because I am going deaf anyway. Or at least, that’s a thing I considered as I was planning to document all this mess. But this is a good news post–I recently got a new set of Apple AirPods Pro, which allows an easy, at-home way to get a hearing test. While this is not a substitute for seeing an audiologist, it’s a nice sanity check that I can share with you.</p>

<p><img src="/i/test.png" alt="test results for your author" /></p>

<p>Besides being an old dude in general, I also played in bands on stage for 11 years, and I am amazed that I seem to have avoided lasting damage from that experience. I was <em>not</em> diligent about hearing protection, and as someone with friends who suffer from a variety of hearing issues, I’d like to encourage anyone to protect their hearing when incurring noise exposure. I do wear my headphones in noise cancel mode when mowing my yard now.</p>

<h2 id="if-its-too-loud-youre-too-old">If it’s too loud, you’re too old</h2>

<p>Well, that may not be the most productive slogan. Mastering engineers try to use a reference level of 83 dB as a consistent benchmark of loudness. I don’t always whip out my meter and check, but my customary listening volumes tend to stay pretty close to that level. It’s loud enough that you won’t be able to carry on a conversation in the room most of the time.</p>

<video controls="" preload="metadata" width="640">
  <source src="/i/level.webm" type="video/webm" />
  <source src="/i/level.mp4" type="video/mp4" />
  Your browser does not support the video tag.
</video>

<blockquote>
  <p>Updated on 2026-01-05</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Rob Arnold</name></author><category term="audio" /><category term="hifi" /><category term="setup" /><category term="hearing" /><category term="measurement" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Investigating how much damage my ears have taken]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">hello again world</title><link href="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/04/hello-again-world.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="hello again world" /><published>2026-01-04T14:34:25-06:00</published><updated>2026-01-04T14:34:25-06:00</updated><id>https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/04/hello-again-world</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://hifi.robarnold.io/audio/hifi/2026/01/04/hello-again-world.html"><![CDATA[<p>Okay, this is the first post on the new blog. In this space, I aim to discuss my learning journey with tuning my hi-fi setup. Most folks struggle to understand the factors that inhibit or enhance the quality of their listening, and it’s not surprising, because acoustics can be challenging if you haven’t had the training to work with measurements in both the time and frequency domain. Since I have an engineering degree (and specialized in signal processing), a lot of the background info needed was included in my education.</p>

<h2 id="overview">Overview</h2>

<p>The most fundamental questions I hope to address for a range of improvement actions are “how much does it improve the sound/listening experience?”, and “how much does it cost?”</p>

<p>I will strive to appeal to measurements and theory whenever possible, but listening to music is a subjective experience, colored by a lot of extrinsic factors. Rather than seeking to eliminate all of these, I just want to acknowledge that it’s one of my aims to not let my biases distract me from pursuing better listening experiences.</p>

<h2 id="reference-materials">Reference materials</h2>

<ul>
  <li>I will be working with <strong>The Master Handbook of Acoustics, Second Edition</strong>, by F. Alton Everest.</li>
  <li>I will refer to the <a href="https://www.roomeqwizard.com/help.html">documentation</a> for Room EQ Wizard software (REW) frequently.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="measurement-gear">Measurement gear</h2>

<ul>
  <li>Behringer ECM-8000 measurement mic (2)</li>
  <li>Edirol UA-25 audio interface (old, but still quite robust)</li>
  <li>Radio Shack 33-2050 sound pressure meter</li>
  <li>REW 5.30</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="images">Images</h2>

<p><img src="/i/IMG_8266.jpeg" alt="a glamour shot of my system" /></p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Updated on 2026-01-04</p>
</blockquote>]]></content><author><name>Rob Arnold</name></author><category term="audio" /><category term="hifi" /><category term="setup" /><category term="klipsch" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Intro post for this new blog]]></summary></entry></feed>